Guide to the Jay Blotcher Papers 1987-2001 MSS.137
Fales Library and Special Collections
Jay Blotcher Papers
1987-2001
Fales Library and Special Collections
MSS.137
4 Linear Feet (5 boxes)
Jay Blotcher dedicated himself to representing the lives of gay and lesbian people through his work as a journalist, publicist, freelance writer, film producer and activist. This collection contains print, media, ephemera, and clothing materials documenting the Lesbian and Gay Rights Movement, AIDS activism and queer activism in the 1990s. The collection includes media releases and other publicity for ACT UP and Queer Nation, two major AIDS and queer advocacy organizations as well as the Anti-Violence Campaign, AmFAR and several smaller organizations.
Provenance
Jay Blotcher donated his papers to Fales Special Collections in May 2003.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions. Please contact the Fales Library and Special Collections, fales.library@nyu.edu, 212-998-2596.
Biographical Note
Jay Blotcher dedicated himself to representing the lives of gays and lesbians through his work as a journalist, publicist, freelance writer, film producer, and activist. His committment to queer activism appeared immediately in his work; his third article for his college newspaper, "The Daily Orange," was a feature on the Gay Student Organization. Queer issues and AIDS activism permeated Blotcher's professional work leading him to represent The American Foundation for AIDS Research (AmFAR), Michelangelo Signorile and numerous other individuals and grassroots organizations. Blotcher's activism intensified when he began work on AIDS issues. In 1987 he joined ACT UP/New York and represented the group at the International AIDS Conferences in Montreal, Amersterdam and Yokohama and served as Media Coordinator for the organization from 1989-1990. Blotcher was a founding member and Media Coordinator for Queer Nation/New York and the executive producer of the Anti-Violence Campaign. Through this professional and activist involvement Jay Blotcher placed himself at the center of AIDS and queer activism in New York and internationally making this collection of great importance to understanding the political environment of the 1990s.
Scope and Content Note
This collection contains print materials, media, ephemera and clothing documenting the Lesbian and Gay Rights Movement, AIDS Activism and Queer Activism in the 1990s. The collection includes media releases and other publicity for ACT UP and Queer Nation, two major AIDS and queer advocacy organizations as well as the Anti-Violence Campaign, AmFAR and several smaller organizations.
Arrangement
Materials have been separated by media. Where possible the collection retains Jay Blotcher's own organization.
Materials in Series I: Printed Materials are arranged alphabetically
Related Material at Fales Library and Special Collections
Alan Klein Papers
Michelangelo Signorile Papers
Separated Material
Select periodicals have been separated from the collection and cataloged individually in Bobcat.
"Lisp" periodical. Premiere Issue. Summer 1995
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Audiovisual and born-digital materials have not been preserved and may not be available to researchers.
Gays -- Political activity -- New York (State) -- New York.; Gay men -- United States.; Gay activists -- New York (State) -- New York.; Washington (D.C.); Yokohama (Japan); Seattle (Wash.); Vancouver (B.C.); Publicity.; In the life (Television program); New York (N.Y.).; Gays in popular culture.; AIDS activists -- New York (State) -- New York; United States |x Armed Forces |x Gays.; Press releases.; Audiocassettes.; Floppy disks.; Clippings (information artifacts); Typescripts.; LGBT activism.; Videocassettes.; International Conference on AIDS; ACT UP (Organization); Rafsky, Bob; Signorile, Michelangelo, 1960-; AmFAR; Housing Works, Inc; Public Impact Media Consultants; Queer Nation (Organization); Alan Klein Media Relations
- Series I: Files and Printed Materials, 9126
  Scope and Contents note
  This series contains clippings, press releases and typescripts relating to Jay Botcher's work as Media Coordinator for ACT UP and Queer Nation as well as materials relating to his work as a publicist for gay and lesbian authors and organizations from 1987-2002.
  - ACT UP: Auction for Action invition. Took place at 890 Broadway, New York. December 3., undated; 9222 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - ACT UP: FBI Files, undated; 9221 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - ACT UP New York: Yokohama, 1994; 9220 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - ACT UP: Political funeral, undated; 9219 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - ACT UP: Rafsky, Bob, undated; 9218 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - ACT UP: Tenth anniversary action, 1997; 9217 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Activism and demonstrations, undated; 9216 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - AIDS and queer clips. Begins September 19, 1991, ca. 1991; 9215 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - AIDS and the media, undated; 9214 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - AIDS education postcards, undated; 9213 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Alan Klein Media Relations media list. September 1, 1994, 9212 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - American Foundation for AIDS Research (AmFAR): AIDS awareness campaign with Kenneth Cole, 1995; 9211 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - AmFAR: Information packet, 1997; 9210 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - AmFAR: Lordly and Dame Inc. Booking Agency, 1995; 9209 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Animal Rights. United Action for Animals and International Society for Animal Rights., 1991; 9208 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - The Anti-Violence Campaign, 1991; 9207 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - The Anti-Violence Campaign: MTV and VHI Anti-gaybashing ads, 1992; 9206 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - The Anti-Violence Campaign: press clips and related articles, ca. 1992; 9205 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - The Anti-Violence Project: Susan Sarandon public service announcement, 1990; 9204 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Astra Pharmaceutical: price inflation of AIDS drug Foscavir AIDS activists and organizations protest., 1991-1992; 9203 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Behrman, Andy: clippings, cards, interviews, undated; 9202 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Behrman, Andy: "Electroboy" typescript, 2001; 9201 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - The Black Party at Roseland, March 19 1994: Advertising poster, 9200 (Box map case, Folder data_value_missing_2c0de2717e7bc5fad448689eb45b8d5f)
  - Blotcher, Jay: personal media list, undated; 9199 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Brooklyn AIDS Task Force: press release, 1991; 9198 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Canadian National AIDS Clearinghouse: postcard, undated; 9197 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Centaur Dance Theatre, 1994; 9196 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - The Center: media releases, 1991; 9195 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Cinema, Queers and AIDS, undated; 9194 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Comedy Central: Out There II, 1994; 9193 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Comedy Central: S. Robbe, 1993; 9192 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - d'Adesy, Anne-Christine, undated; 9191 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Donat, Hank "Popcorn in the Morning" typescript, undated; 9190 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - A few good queers, undated; 9189 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - The Flirtations. Gay musical group., 1992; 9188 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Gay City Health Project, Seattle Washington, 1995; 9187 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Gay and Lesbian Alliance Against Defamation (GLAAD): Mediagram campaign, 1991; 9186 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - GLAAD: Trojan War, 1991; 9185 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - "Gotham gals hanker for other hunks" [Jay Blotcher quoted in article] New York Post. July 16, 1993, 9184 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - "Hallowe'en Mystery" by Jay Blotcher, grade 5. Martin E. Young School, undated; 9183 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Harry Paul and Associates letterhead, undated; 9182 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Hennelly, Christopher: Police brutality case, 1991; 9181 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Hetrick-Martin Institute: Volunteer orientation packet, undated; 9180 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Housing Works "Demonstrators Slam Lack of AIDS Housing" Newsday article. September 13, 1993, 9179 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - "In the Life" media releases, clippings and program guides, undated; 9178 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Institute for Gay and Lesbian Strategic Studies. Working group on funding. "Creating Communities: Giving and Volunteering by Gay, Lesbian, Bisexual, and Transgender People.", 1998; 9177 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - International Conference on AIDS. Postcard for the 11th conference, Vancouver Canada. July 7-12, 1996., 9176 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - "Johnny Guitar" with Ryan Landry and Kandi Kane. Presented by the Gold Dust Orphans Antro Theatre, Provincetown MA, undated; 9175 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Lesbian and Gay Directory of Services and Resources, 1997; 9174 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Lesbian and Gay People of Color Steering Committee Participating Organizations, undated; 9173 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Lesbian and Gay Teachers Association Media advisory, undated; 9172 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Media Mavens resources list. November 17, 1989, 9171 (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - Military Murders, Gay Ban, Petrelis in Japan, undated; 9170 (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - Mr. Leather New York. Organizing committe certificate of recognition, 1996; 9169 (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - National Lesbian and Gay Journalists Association convention. "Making Waves" Hyatt Regency, Miami FL. September 5-8, 1996, 9168 (Box 2, Folder 54)
  - National Gay and Lesbian Task Force. Press release, 1991; 9167 (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - New York Advertising and Communications Network membership directory, 1996-1997; 9166 (Box 2, Folder 56)
  - NYC Parents and Friends of Lesbians and Gays [PFLAG] salutes Dick Ashworth. May 11, 1998, 9165 (Box 2, Folder 57)
  - Nocturnal, 1993; 9164 (Box 2, Folder 58)
  - Outfest. Los Angeles Gay and Lesbian Film Festival, 1997; 9163 (Box 2, Folder 59)
  - Out Loud lesbian and gay cultural and business expo., 1994; 9162 (Box 2, Folder 60)
  - "Out There" comedy special, 1993; 9161 (Box 2, Folder 61)
  - Out Write: the fifth national lesbian and gay writers conference., 1995; 9160 (Box 2, Folder 62)
  - Percy William. "Outing: Shattering the Conspiracy of Silence", 1994; 9159 (Box 2, Folder 63)
  - Planet Q: The Queer Comedy Troup. "Homo Alone, Lost in Colorado", 1993; 9158 (Box 2, Folder 64)
  - POZ: Health, Hope and HIV. March 1997., 9157 (Box 2, Folder 65)
  - Project Inform: treatment information packet., undated; 9156 (Box 2, Folder 66)
  - Public Impact Media Consultants: queer media list, August 1994., 9155 (Box 2, Folder 67)
  - Queer Nation, 1990; 9154 (Box 2, Folder 68)
  - Queer Nation letterhead, undated; 9153 (Box 2, Folder 69)
  - Rainbow Run for the end of AIDS, 1990; 9152 (Box 2, Folder 70)
  - Reed, Phillip. City Council candidate, 1997; 9151 (Box 2, Folder 71)
  - RFSL: the Swedish Federation for Gay and Lesbian Rights. "Lesbian and Gay the Swedish Way.", 1994; 9150 (Box 2, Folder 72)
  - Sadownick, Douglas. "Sacred Lips of the Bronx" press packet., undated; 9149 (Box 2, Folder 73)
  - Senior Action in a Gay Environment (SAGE) Dance Marathon at the Limelight., 1991; 9148 (Box 2, Folder 74)
  - SAGE Dance Marathon at the Roxy., 1992; 9147 (Box 2, Folder 75)
  - SAGE tribute to Lorenz Hart, 1991; 9146 (Box 2, Folder 76)
  - Sedarbaum, Ed. New York State Senate campaign, 1997; 9145 (Box 2, Folder 77)
  - Sex Information and Education Council of the US (SEICUS) Study Guide #2: Homosexuality., undated; 9144 (Box 2, Folder 78)
  - "Sex is...exploring the meaning of sex and sexuality..." Film by Marc Huestis and Lawrence Helman., 1993; 9143 (Box 2, Folder 79)
  - Signorile, Michelangelo: columns, undated; 9142 (Box 2, Folder 80)
  - Signorile, Michelangelo: "Life Outside" Armistead Maupin quote., 1997; 9141 (Box 2, Folder 81)
  - Signorile, Michelangelo: publicity for "Life Outside", undated; 9140 (Box 2, Folder 82)
  - Signorile, Michelangelo: "Life Outside" typescript, undated; 9139 (Box 2, Folder 83)
  - Signorile, Michelangelo: "Outing Yourself" News from Randomhouse, undated; 9138 (Box 2, Folder 84)
  - Signorile, Michelangelo: "Outing Yourself" project planner, multiple dates; 9137 (Box 2, Folder 85)
  - Signorile, Michelangelo: "Outing Yourself" typescript, undated; 9136 (Box 2, Folder 86)
  - Signorile, Michelangelo: "Queer in America" College tour bookings., 1995; 9135 (Box 2, Folder 87)
  - Signorile, Michelangelo: "Queer in America" press packet, undated; 9134 (Box 2, Folder 88)
  - Signorile, Michelangelo: "Queer in America" typescript, undated; 9133 (Box 2, Folder 89)
  - Signorile, Michelangelo: Speaking engagements, undated; 9132 (Box 2, Folder 90)
  - Television, Queers and AIDS, undated; 9131 (Box 2, Folder 91)
  - United Voices, United Visions committee lists, June 10, 1995., 9130 (Box 2, Folder 92)
  - "Voices from the Front" Frameline release, 1992; 9129 (Box 2, Folder 93)
  - "When AIDS Ends" by Andrew Sullivan, New York Times Magazine, November 10, 1996, 9128 (Box 2, Folder 94)
  - "Wilde" special screening invitation, 1998; 9127 (Box 2, Folder 95)
- Series II: Media, 9103
  Audio cassettes, microcassettes, floppy disks and videocassettes containing articles, interviews, music and programs relating to Jay Blotcher's activism and interests.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Audiovisual and born-digital materials have not been preserved and may not be available to researchers.
  - The Glass Spider Tour, David Bowie in Concert. Giants Stadium, NJ August., undated; 9125 (Box 3, Folder 137)
    Currently unavailable until duplication occurs.
    Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements note
    Original format: Microcassette, Sony MC60
  - Burroughs Welcome coverage. April 25, 1989, 9124 (Box 3, Folder 137)
    Original format: Microcassette, AIWA MC-30
  - MacLeod, undated; 9123 (Box 3, Folder 137)
    Original format: Microcassette, Maxell MC-60
  - Meat Puppets and Marianne Faithfull, undated; 9122 (Box 3, Folder 137)
  - Mildred Pierced, May 11, 1987; 9121 (Box 3, Folder 137)
  - Rollerena Tape 1, undated; 9120 (Box 3, Folder 137.001)
  - 2nd part of Rollerena Part I, undated; 9119 (Box 3, Folder 137.001)
  - Phone Messages, July and September, 1991; 9118 (Box 3, Folder 137.001)
    Original format: Microcassette, TDK
  - Phone Messages, undated; 9117 (Box 3, Folder 137.001)
    Original format: Microcassette, Panasonic RT-30MC
  - Unlabeled except for date 1994-1996, 9116 (Box 3, Folder 137.001)
    Original format: Microcassette, Panasonic MC-30
  - unlabeled, undated; 9115 (Box 3, Folder 137.001)
    Original format: Microcassette, TDK MC60
  - Alternet Gay and Lesbian Radio for South Florida. Program #26. Includes: Adoption Ban for Gays ruled unconstitutional in Sarasota; Florida lawmaker from Davie withdraws civil rights bill; Navy claims gay sailor was murdered by gay ex-lover; California city legally defines 'family'; This gay in history did it on stage: Colin Higgins; A report on gay women in the military; Making an artistic statement: art about AIDS; To buy or not to buy: that is the question of boycotts; Music: Hosework! and Dykes!!, March 7, 1993; 9114 (Box 3, Folder 137.001)
    Original format: Audiocassette, TDK D60
  - Larry King Show, Michelangelo Signorile., May 19, 1993; 9113 (Box 3, Folder 137.001)
    Original format: Audiocassette, unmarked
  - ACT UP on 60 Minutes featuring Peter Staley, Bob Rafsky and Marina Alvarez., November 15, 1992; 9112 (Box 3, Folder 137.001)
    Original format: VHS, Maxell EX-120
  - Box labeled: "Video compilation of erotica in mainstream TV and film. By SF journalist Jim Provenzano" Home-made cover. Cassette labeled: Jay's Jo Jumpin Joy Juice Jumble., undated; 9111 (Box 3, Folder 137.002)
    Original format: VHS, Fuji high quality, tape damaged
  - Outweek articles and Tetris, undated; 9110 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    3.5 inch floppy disk, unlabeled
  - Outweek, SYR Mag Files, Games files, undated; 9109 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    3.5 inch floppy disk, 3M double side 1.0 MB
  - Resume 1995, Applications and Utils., Out Mag pieces, Out Loud expos, GAA reunion, Comedy Skits, Miles, Lisp, New article ideas, 1260 LSM, Splash, 9108 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    3.5 inch floppy disk, TDK MF-2HD
  - Queer in America, undated; 9107 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    3.5 inch floppy disk, Fuji film, MF2DD
  - Queries, Joey Pons 2145, Cruse, Out-Gean, undated; 9106 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    3.5 inch floppy disk, 3M DS, HD 1.4 Mb
  - Sex Club Article, complete; profile of Howard Cruse, January 29, 1996; 9105 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    3.5 inch floppy disk, HD
  - Sex Clubs, Howard Cruse article, undated; 9104 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Series III: Ephemera, 9082
  Materials including pins, nametags, pens and magnets relating to Jay Blotcher's activism and professional work for Queer Nation, ACT UP and the Lesbian and Gay rights movement.
  - Square button. "ACT UP Fight Back Fight AIDS", undated; 9102 (Box 4, Folder data_value_missing_4cc58788710422291aaa329ecf5e0071)
  - Circular button. "Queer in America", undated; 9101 (Box 4, Folder data_value_missing_229dfc1410420d930267a2bb18d08830)
  - Circular button. "He's Gotta Have It!", undated; 9100 (Box 4, Folder data_value_missing_8de8112816b9a66532588ebf4dfef159)
  - Circular button, missing pin. "Try 31. For a Change. WNYC-TV" Paper pink triangle with words "our time" pasted on., undated; 9099 (Box 4, Folder data_value_missing_327aa796a4482527ef00c471d8d9207d)
  - circular button. "Silence=Death", undated; 9098 (Box 4, Folder data_value_missing_9e8c3cbb11a227ef2d9ded89dd103e58)
  - Rectangular button. "Rainbow Run for the End of AIDS San Francisco to Vancouver. June 7th-August 4th 1990. In Honor of Tom Waddell and Keith Haring.", 9097 (Box 4, Folder data_value_missing_c3b9e0ed5d87499a4ce91c9d07c18f38)
  - Circular button. "Hot Sex Now", undated; 9096 (Box 4, Folder data_value_missing_d0fb6f6bd5a840262e1f0c3d3768861f)
  - Circular button. "Ramrod Anniversary XVI", undated; 9095 (Box 4, Folder data_value_missing_337bdb2f36118810dd224a6b66beb197)
  - Circular button. [Trans activist, Marsha P. Johnson], undated; 9094 (Box 4, Folder data_value_missing_fad1fdddfaed354d01ee2550f08e498c)
  - Circular button. "ACT UP", undated; 9093 (Box 4, Folder data_value_missing_f14c77be9327934109b6f4f41afd2b69)
  - Circular button. "Silence=Mort 1989 Silence=Death project", 9092 (Box 4, Folder data_value_missing_96d8883fc563747c70283c75fff676ca)
  - Lighter, undated; 9091 (Box 4, Folder data_value_missing_14aab6ef91bd7a63018cc18fed8a5064)
  - Rectangular sticker. "PM Chretien We're Dying for a National AIDS Strategy", undated; 9090 (Box 4, Folder data_value_missing_ce3f2ee8ef0264386e0c057de1fda070)
  - 30 round stickers. "Queer in America", undated; 9089 (Box 4, Folder data_value_missing_18235b0e0a04d5ba72c4fd4eca672a10)
  - Postcard from the Beverly Prescott hotel. " 'When a shower just won't do' The Beverly Prescott's King Jacuzzi Room", undated; 9088 (Box 4, Folder data_value_missing_4010a819b74fcfa6efa4a45a51b90f6f)
  - Rectangular Magnet. "The Pants Too? Yes, Please Donate. Out of the closet thrift store and AIDS healthcare foundation.", undated; 9087 (Box 4, Folder data_value_missing_ad598afc254b03df73424148b6f97449)
  - XI International Conference on AIDS nametag. "Jay Blotcher- The Front Page" With Durex pen., undated; 9086 (Box 4, Folder data_value_missing_572fcdd47d2b1cb4e27ae7870f00a600)
  - Necklace. One side "ACT UP for a cure" Opposite side "1992 March on Washington for Lesbian, Gay and Bi Equal Rights and Liberation.", 9085 (Box 4, Folder data_value_missing_d372b3594ad3d1791b99b88eb5f8d222)
  - One pencil. " 'Pageant' - NY's Nightly Beauty Contest", undated; 9084 (Box 4, Folder data_value_missing_c412b4e69e08e240a5fd68e41df1185d)
  - One pen. "Wolf Talk Radio 1490AM, 96.7 FM", undated; 9083 (Box 4, Folder data_value_missing_d1f9a265d007ca3fcd211246a105e292)
- Series IV: Clothing, 9077
  Series IV contains t-shirts and a sweatshirt related to Jay Blotcher's professional career, activism and interests. All of series IV is located in Box 5, which is an OVERSIZE box.
  - T-shirt. "Q" "Queer Nation", undated; 9081 (Oversize 5)
  - T-shirt. "Some of my best friends are Queer in America", undated; 9080 (Oversize 5)
  - T-shirt. Photograph. [Liam Neeson], undated; 9079 (Oversize 5)
  - Sweatshirt. "Queer Nation get used to it!", undated; 9078 (Oversize 5)